# 芝麻豌豆蓉
# 半个世纪前的甜品
Pea Milk with Sesame
A Dessert from Half a Century Ago
# 趁你们不注意我把芝麻炒熟了
I've already toasted the sesame when you didn't notice
# 您这水也开了
The water is also boiling
# 水开了吧
Water's boiling
# 得 二伯
OK, Er Bai
# 您这伸把手吧
Please give me a hand
# 这芝麻啊得炒一下
# （白芝麻小火烘香擀成芝麻碎） # 副字幕，持续时间较长
Gotta toast the sesame
(Toast the white sesame over low heat, then grind it)
# 炒多少分钟啊
# （白芝麻小火烘香擀成芝麻碎）
For how long?
(Toast the white sesame over low heat, then grind it)
# 还是炒什么样啊
# （白芝麻小火烘香擀成芝麻碎）
Or to what stage?
(Toast the white sesame over low heat, then grind it)
# 标准？
# （白芝麻小火烘香擀成芝麻碎）
Any standards?
(Toast the white sesame over low heat, then grind it)
# 炒到金黄色
# （白芝麻小火烘香擀成芝麻碎）
To golden brown
(Toast the white sesame over low heat, then grind it)
# 酥香
Crispy and aromatic
# 有味儿
And flavorful
# 你看 给擀成芝麻碎
Look, gotta grind the sesame
# 实际上芝麻碎的芝麻香味释放的更充分
Actually, the aroma is more fully released after grinding
# 你看大爷很会选菜
You know, Da Ye is good at picking a dish
# 我选的是应季菜
I picked a seasonal dish
# 今天呢做一甜品
# （芝麻豌豆蓉 大爷五十年前学会的一道传统的甜菜）# 副字幕，持续时间较长
Today, we'll make a dessert
(Pea Milk with Sesame, a traditional dissert Da Ye learnt 50 years ago)
# 实际上中餐呢不叫甜品
# （芝麻豌豆蓉 大爷五十年前学会的一道传统的甜菜）
Actually, we don't call it a dessert in Chinese cuisine
(Pea Milk with Sesame, a traditional sweet dish Da Ye learnt 50 years ago)
# - 叫甜菜 - 对
# （芝麻豌豆蓉 大爷五十年前学会的一道传统的甜菜）
- We call it "Tian Cai" ("sweet dish") - Yeah
(Pea Milk with Sesame, a traditional sweet dish Da Ye learnt 50 years ago)
# - 西餐叫甜品 - 对
# （芝麻豌豆蓉 大爷五十年前学会的一道传统的甜菜）
- In western cuisine, it's "dessert" - Yeah
(Pea Milk with Sesame, a traditional sweet dish Da Ye learnt 50 years ago)
# 我们把这豌豆做完以后拿粉碎机
# （芝麻豌豆蓉 大爷五十年前学会的一道传统的甜菜）
Let's get the peas done, and then use a blender
(Pea Milk with Sesame, a traditional sweet dish Da Ye learnt 50 years ago)
# 把它打成蓉
# （现在已经很少出现在大众消费的餐桌上了）
to make it into a mince
(It's now rarely seen in most restaurants)
# 打成蓉以后下锅呢
# （现在已经很少出现在大众消费的餐桌上了）
Then we cook the mince
(It's now rarely seen in most restaurants)
# 把它勾成豌豆蓉
# （现在已经很少出现在大众消费的餐桌上了）
and turn it into pea milk
(It's now rarely seen in most restaurants)
# 撒上芝麻搁上白糖
# （现在已经很少出现在大众消费的餐桌上了）
Then we sprinkle some sesame and sugar on it
(It's now rarely seen in most restaurants)
# 这也可以做成汤
It can also be made into a soup
# 不搁芝麻碎了 搁点干贝
Instead of sesame, we add some dried scallops
# 搁点虾仁儿
Add some shrimps
# 你看这个是翠绿的吧 虾仁是红的
This is green, isn't it? And shrimps are red
# 把虾仁给切碎
We chop up the shrimps
# 豌豆蓉虾仁羹
"Pea milk soup with shrimps"
# 吃咸的时候要有点好汤啊
Gotta have some nice soup when eating something salty
# 这个适合我们小孩啊老年人啊
That's good for kids and elderlies
# 出锅
Take it out
# - 用冲一下凉水么 - 要冲啊
- Cold water? - Yeah
# 没有粉碎机的时候我们可以煮的时间长一点
When without a blender, we can stew it for longer
# 拿手一撵那个豆儿就成了泥儿了
You can mash it with your hand
# 以那个为标准
That's the standard
# 其实有点豆儿有点口感么
What if we leave some peas for a texture?
# 有渣子
Leave some husk
# 不行 一定要柔滑
No. It has to be smooth
# 过一下凉
Through the cold water
# 翠绿翠绿的啊
It's so green, huh
# 碧绿
Emerald green
# 有芝麻搁芝麻
Add some sesame if you have sesame
# 有松子仁儿搁松子仁儿
Add pine nuts if you have pine nuts
# 有桃仁儿搁桃仁儿
Add peach nuts if you have peach nuts
# 搁什么是什么香味儿
You get the flavor for what you add
# 打得细就让他多转会儿
We want it fine. Let it run for a while
# 您这个还真够绿的
Wow, you made it so green
# 过箩啊
Strain it
# 过一下箩
Through the strainer
# 找一小勺攉拢攉拢
Stir it with a spoon
# 忘了带一大箩了
I forgot to take a bigger strainer
# 行 这点儿够了
Alright, enough
# 不行不行 不够
No, no, not enough
# 你不接点水它哪儿够啊
If you don't add some water, it's not gonna be enough
# 涮涮 涮一下倒里头
Rinse it, and pour it in
# 别浪费
No wasting
# 过滤出来的渣子就是它那豆皮儿了
The residue left in the strainer is the pea skin
# 这个有时候我们也不扔
We don't always throw it away
# 再来一点
Some more
# 蒸点面食 做个饺子馅儿
to steam some pastry, or make some dumpling filling
# 好了
Alright
# 擦擦汗
Wipe the sweat
# 对 您脑袋自己动
Right, move your head yourself please
# 活儿齐了
All done
# 来点儿淀粉
Get some starch
# 看着啊快开了啊
Watch it, it's gonna boil
# 开了呢咱就先勾芡后放糖
When it boils, we add slurry first, and then sugar
# 为什么不能先放糖啊
Why can't we add sugar first
# 一会一晃啊 这边上容易糊边儿
The sugar on the side of the wok might burn
# 锅开了啊
It's boiling
# 勾芡
Add slurry
# 放糖
Add sugar
# 这就是原汁原味
That's the original flavor
# 出锅咯 过箩
Done! Strain it
# 这搁俩虾仁真漂亮
It will be so pretty with some shrimps
# 红红的小虾仁
Red little shrimps
# 虾仁碎是吧
Yeah, chopped shrimps
# 您动
You move, please
# 现在搁是香
More aromatic if we add it now
# 这个晾凉了搁也好喝
Also good if we wait until it cools down
# 我觉得还是喝凉的
I prefer it cool
# 好啦 主要体现这豆味儿
Done! It emphasizes the pea flavor
# 这豆味儿够浓的啦
What a strong pea flavor
# 然后就芝麻香味儿
And also the aroma of the sesame
# 好啦
Alright
# 喝上了啊二伯
Let's get started, Er Bai
# 怎么样感觉
How does it feel?
# 甜度正好
Just the right level of sweetness
# 水也合适
Also the right amount of water
# 再说回来了
And you know what
# 粥跟这没法比
This is way better than congee
# 在他们家他不使这个白糖
He doesn't use white sugar at his own home
# 在他们家他自己做他使冰糖
He uses rock sugar instead
# 给咱们的就是白糖
When cooking for us, white sugar only
# 没有啦
I'm done
# 没有啦？
Done?
# 再给来一碗
Another bowl for you
# import ending.sbv 0:04:22.760